<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!--

eponyms-touch
Eponyms Data © by Andrew J. Yee
This data is formally excluded from the Apache License

-->
<!DOCTYPE eponyms [
	<!ELEMENT category (tag, title)>
	<!ELEMENT eponym (id, name, desc, cat*, c?, e?)>
	<!ELEMENT name (#PCDATA)>
	<!ELEMENT desc (#PCDATA)>
	<!ELEMENT cat (#PCDATA)>
	<!ELEMENT c (#PCDATA)>
	<!ELEMENT e (#PCDATA)>
]>
<root created="1258304812">

<category tag="ANAT" title="Anatomy" />
<category tag="GI" title="Gastroenterology" />
<category tag="PEDS" title="Pediatrics" />
<category tag="SYND" title="Syndromes" />
<category tag="DERM" title="Dermatology" />
<category tag="PATH" title="Pathology" />
<category tag="ENDO" title="Endocrinology" />
<category tag="OPHTH" title="Ophthalmology" />
<category tag="NEURO" title="Neurology" />
<category tag="SIGN" title="Signs" />
<category tag="GYN" title="Gynecology" />
<category tag="ORTHO" title="Orthopedics" />
<category tag="PROC" title="Procedures and Tests" />
<category tag="CV" title="Cardiovascular" />
<category tag="HEME" title="Hematology" />
<category tag="ENT" title="Ear, Nose and Throat" />
<category tag="PULM" title="Pulmonary" />
<category tag="RENAL" title="Renal" />
<category tag="BIOCHEM" title="Biochemistry and Metabolism" />
<category tag="RAYS" title="Radiology" />
<category tag="RHEUM" title="Rheumatology" />
<category tag="ONC" title="Oncology" />
<category tag="OB" title="Obstetrics" />
<category tag="ID" title="Infectious Disease" />
<category tag="URO" title="Urology" />
<category tag="PSYCH" title="Psychiatry" />
<category tag="GEO" title="Geographical" />
<category tag="MISC" title="Miscellaneous" />

<eponym id="Abernethymalformation">
	<name>Abernethy malformation</name>
	<desc>Congenital anomaly of the splanchnic vasculature, arises from defects in vitelline vein formation; in type 1, portal vein completely diverted into IVC and complete absence of formation of intrahepatic portal vein; in type 2, portal venous system is formed, but there is an abnormal communication with systemic veins, usually IVC; associated with hepatic encephalopathy and hepatopulmonary syndrome; more common in dogs, particularly Yorkshire terriers.</desc>
	<cat>ANAT</cat>
	<cat>GI</cat>
	<cat>PEDS</cat>
	<c>1/17/2005</c>
	<e>6/22/2009</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="Achenbachssyndrome">
	<name>Achenbach's syndrome</name>
	<desc>Rare entity of spontaneous or mechanically-induced hematomas on the volar aspect of fingers associated with burning pain and swelling of the digits.</desc>
	<cat>SYND</cat>
	<cat>DERM</cat>
	<c>4/5/2007</c>
	<e>4/5/2007</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="Adamkiewiczarteryof">
	<name>Adamkiewicz, artery of</name>
	<desc>Artery that when severed, can lead to anterior spinal syndrome; can be severed in abdominal aortic aneurysm repair.</desc>
	<cat>ANAT</cat>
	<c>3/21/1998</c>
	<e>6/29/2009</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="Adamsonsfringe">
	<name>Adamson's fringe</name>
	<desc>In tinea capitis, the location of the terminal tuft of hyphae; weakest point of hair located just about Adamson's fringe.</desc>
	<cat>DERM</cat>
	<cat>PATH</cat>
	<cat>ANAT</cat>
	<c>8/21/2000</c>
	<e>8/21/2000</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="Addisonsdisease">
	<name>Addison's disease</name>
	<desc>Primary adrenal insufficiency. Bilateral adrenal destruction by tuberculosis used to be most common cause, now only accounts for 7-20% of cases. Now autoimmune disease 70-90%, remainder caused by infectious disease, metastasis or lymphoma, adrenal hemorrhage, infarction, or drugs.</desc>
	<cat>ENDO</cat>
	<c>8/21/2000</c>
	<e>8/21/2000</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="Adiespupil">
	<name>Ädie's pupil</name>
	<desc>Tonic pupil, larger than contralateral unaffected pupil, reacts sluggishly to changes in illumination; see also Holmes-Adie syndrome; seen in young women; no neurologic significance.</desc>
	<cat>OPHTH</cat>
	<cat>NEURO</cat>
	<c>3/21/1998</c>
	<e>3/21/1998</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="Adlersign">
	<name>Adler sign</name>
	<desc>For distinguishing appendicitis from adnexal or uterine pain: if the point of maximal tenderness shifts medially with repositioning on the left lateral side, etiology generally gynecologic.</desc>
	<cat>GI</cat>
	<cat>SIGN</cat>
	<cat>GYN</cat>
	<c>7/19/2006</c>
	<e>6/29/2009</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="Adsonssign">
	<name>Adson's sign</name>
	<desc>In thoracic outlet syndrome, decrease in ipsilateral radial pulse and/or presence of subclavian bruit while patient extending neck maximally, rotating head towards side being tested, and holding breath.</desc>
	<cat>ORTHO</cat>
	<cat>PROC</cat>
	<cat>SIGN</cat>
	<cat>CV</cat>
	<c>2/28/2000</c>
	<e>6/18/2009</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="AhumadadelCastillosyndrome">
	<name>Ahumada-del Castillo syndrome</name>
	<desc>Galactorrhea-amenorrhea not associated with pregnancy.</desc>
	<cat>ENDO</cat>
	<cat>SYND</cat>
	<c>5/25/2001</c>
	<e>5/25/2001</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="Aicardisyndrome">
	<name>Aicardi syndrome</name>
	<desc>Partial or complete agenesis of corpus callosum, infantile spasms, mental retardation, lacunae of the retina; occurs only in females; likely X-linked dominant with lethality in males; described in 1965.</desc>
	<cat>PEDS</cat>
	<cat>NEURO</cat>
	<cat>OPHTH</cat>
	<cat>SYND</cat>
	<c>12/14/2002</c>
	<e>7/30/2009</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="Babinskisign">
	<name>Babinski sign</name>
	<desc>Normally plantar response where toes flex in response to sole of foot being stroked; upgoing toes are an upper motor sign that indicates dysfunction of fibers within the pyramidal system; described in 1896 by Babinski, student of Charcot.</desc>
	<cat>NEURO</cat>
	<cat>SIGN</cat>
	<cat>PROC</cat>
	<c>3/25/2000</c>
	<e>1/23/2009</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="Bachmannsbundle">
	<name>Bachmann's bundle</name>
	<desc>Anterior internodal tract in atrial conduction system.</desc>
	<cat>CV</cat>
	<cat>ANAT</cat>
	<c>2/28/2000</c>
	<e>2/28/2000</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="Bainbridgereflex">
	<name>Bainbridge reflex</name>
	<desc>Compensatory increase in heart rate caused by a rise in right atrial pressure.</desc>
	<cat>CV</cat>
	<c>2/28/2000</c>
	<e>2/28/2000</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="Bakerscyst">
	<name>Baker's cyst</name>
	<desc>Popliteal cyst, a synovial cyst within the popliteal fossa.</desc>
	<cat>RHEUM</cat>
	<cat>ORTHO</cat>
	<c>2/28/2000</c>
	<e>7/1/2009</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="Balintssyndrome">
	<name>Balint's syndrome</name>
	<desc>Optic ataxia (inability to visually guide limb movements), ocular ataxia (inability to direct eyes to a precise point in the visual field), inability to enumerate objects in a picture or extract meaning from a picture, and inability to avoid objects in one's path, simultanagnosia (can only process one object at a time), from infarction in unilateral or bilateral visual association area due to watershed stroke between distal PCA and MCA.</desc>
	<cat>NEURO</cat>
	<cat>OPHTH</cat>
	<cat>SYND</cat>
	<c>3/6/2000</c>
	<e>3/6/2000</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="Balkannephropathy">
	<name>Balkan nephropathy</name>
	<desc>Degenerative interstitial nephropathy seen in Balkan areas (tributaries of Danube River), with tubular proteinuria, glycosuria, renal tubular acidosis, azotemia, associated with increased risk of upper tract transitional cell carcinoma. Hypothesized to be from chronic exposure to dietary aristolochic acid from Aristolochia clematitis, a plant native to endemic areas.</desc>
	<cat>RENAL</cat>
	<cat>SYND</cat>
	<cat>GEO</cat>
	<c>2/28/2000</c>
	<e>6/30/2009</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="Ballancessign">
	<name>Ballance's sign</name>
	<desc>Tender mass in the left upper quadrant due to a spleen hematoma.</desc>
	<cat>GI</cat>
	<cat>SIGN</cat>
	<c>2/28/2000</c>
	<e>2/28/2000</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="Ballsdisease">
	<name>Ball's disease</name>
	<desc>Intracerebral leukocytostasis, a potentially fatal complication of acute leukemia (especially AML) when peripheral blast cell count &gt;100,000/uL; leukemic cells capable of invading through endothelium and causing hemorrhage into brain. Condition not generally seen with CLL or CML.</desc>
	<cat>HEME</cat>
	<cat>ONC</cat>
	<cat>NEURO</cat>
	<c>3/5/2000</c>
	<e>8/21/2008</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="Balsdisease">
	<name>Baló's disease</name>
	<desc>Variant of multiple sclerosis, see concentric rings of demyelination separated by bands of preserved myelin.</desc>
	<cat>NEURO</cat>
	<c>8/8/2001</c>
	<e>8/8/2001</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="Balticmyoclonus">
	<name>Baltic myoclonus</name>
	<desc>See Unverricht-Lundborg disease.</desc>
	<cat>NEURO</cat>
	<cat>SYND</cat>
	<cat>GEO</cat>
	<c>9/2/2002</c>
	<e>7/27/2009</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="Cabotring">
	<name>Cabot ring</name>
	<desc>In asplenia or malfunctional spleen, nuclear remnants on red blood cells as a thin, darkly-stained ring that follows the margin of the red cell.</desc>
	<cat>PATH</cat>
	<cat>HEME</cat>
	<c>3/21/1998</c>
	<e>8/23/2008</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="Cabrerassign">
	<name>Cabrera's sign</name>
	<desc>In left bundle branch block complicated by myocardial infarction, notching at 0.05 s in ascending limb of S wave in V3, V4; 27% sensitive for MI.</desc>
	<cat>CV</cat>
	<cat>SIGN</cat>
	<c>2/28/2000</c>
	<e>1/12/2002</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="CacchiRiccidisease">
	<name>Cacchi-Ricci disease</name>
	<desc>Medullary sponge kidney disease.</desc>
	<cat>RENAL</cat>
	<c>8/2/2003</c>
	<e>8/2/2003</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="CADASIL">
	<name>CADASIL</name>
	<desc>Cerebral Autosomal Dominant Arteropathy with Subcortical Infarcts and Leukoencephalopathy, a rare hereditary cause of stroke that may involve Notch3 gene characterized by recurrent strokes (usually infarcts) and dementia.</desc>
	<cat>NEURO</cat>
	<cat>SYND</cat>
	<c>2/28/2000</c>
	<e>2/28/2000</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="Cagotear">
	<name>Cagot ear</name>
	<desc>Absence of ear lobe; associated with region in Pyrennes.</desc>
	<cat>ENT</cat>
	<cat>GEO</cat>
	<c>3/7/2003</c>
	<e>8/13/2009</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="caissondisease">
	<name>caisson disease</name>
	<desc>Decompression sickness.</desc>
	<cat>MISC</cat>
	<cat>GEO</cat>
	<c>3/21/1998</c>
	<e>6/30/2009</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="Cajalinterstitialcellsof">
	<name>Cajal, interstitial cells of</name>
	<desc>Cells present as networks of cells associated with neural plexues within gut musculature; required for normal intestinal motility.</desc>
	<cat>GI</cat>
	<cat>ANAT</cat>
	<c>1/25/2004</c>
	<e>1/25/2004</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="Calabarswellings">
	<name>Calabar swellings</name>
	<desc>In loiasis, swellings 5-10 cm in diameter from localized areas of angioedema associated with migration of adult Loa loa worms through subcutaneous tissues.</desc>
	<cat>ID</cat>
	<cat>DERM</cat>
	<c>6/2/2001</c>
	<e>6/2/2001</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="CallExnerbodies">
	<name>Call-Exner bodies</name>
	<desc>In granulosa cell tumors involving ovary, small follicles filled with eosinophilic secretion; an important diagnostic feature.</desc>
	<cat>PATH</cat>
	<cat>GYN</cat>
	<cat>ONC</cat>
	<c>3/21/1998</c>
	<e>8/23/2008</e>
</eponym>
<eponym id="CallFlemingsyndrome">
	<name>Call-Fleming syndrome</name>
	<desc>Sudden-onset severe headache, focal neurological deficits, and seizures; associated with serotonin modulating drugs like SSRIs.</desc>
	<cat>NEURO</cat>
	<cat>SYND</cat>
	<c>3/3/2003</c>
	<e>3/3/2003</e>
</eponym>

</root>
